<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of the city of Oxford. Shewing how far they are concerned to oppose the confirmation of the charters and pretended priviledges of the University With an answer to a late pamphlet printed at Oxford, entituled, A defence of the rights and priviledges of the University of Oxford.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1034B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230053</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895888</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895888</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78239)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153440)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2365:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of the city of Oxford. Shewing how far they are concerned to oppose the confirmation of the charters and pretended priviledges of the University With an answer to a late pamphlet printed at Oxford, entituled, A defence of the rights and priviledges of the University of Oxford.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: A defence of the rights and priviledges of the University of Oxford.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>University of Oxford --  Charters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Defence of the rights and priviledges of the University of Oxford --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oxford (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153440:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE OF THE City of OXFORD.</p>
            <p>SHEWING How far they are concerned to Oppoſe the Confirmation of the Charters and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Priviledges of the UNIVERSITY.</p>
            <p>WITH AN Anſwer to a late Pamphlet Printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> Entituled, <hi>A Defence of the Rights and Priviledges of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Oxford.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT is now Three Years and more ſince the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> firſt troubled the World and both Houſes of Parliament with the Charter <hi>11 Car. 1.</hi> we are ſorry they ſhould think this the moſt favourable Conjuncture which hath happened theſe Threeſcore Years to eſtabliſh Arbitrary Power in <hi>Oxford,</hi> when the Nation is in full poſſeſſion of Liberty, and hath lately reſcued it ſelf by Arms from Slavery and Oppreſſion. Thoſe Gentlemen could not bear the Yoak themſelves, but would lay a more intolerable one upon us, and make the City of <hi>Oxford</hi> the only place that hath no Inheritance in the Laws of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reverend, and never to be forgotten Biſhop <hi>Fell,</hi> who was a true Patron and Guardian of the Univerſity, whoſe Heart and Soul were in their Intereſt, never attempted a Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Charter, but was contented with thoſe wiſe and moderate Men that went before him, to reſerve it in Chains of Darkneſs; and it had undoubtedly been conſigned to everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reſt, had not the ſpirits of ſome few Men diſturbed its quiet, and forced it into Publick.</p>
            <p>It had unqueſtionably been more Wiſe and Honourable for that Great and Venerable Body to have buried this Charter in the ſame Grave with that Reverend Prelate that procured it, than to ſet it up at this day, to convince the World, that nothing will ſatisfie them but the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of an Arbitrary Power over their Neighbours eſtabliſhed by Law; for let them pretend what they will, they cannot produce one Article in that whole Charter (beſides that of Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) which may be ſerviceable to the Honour of God, the Advancement of Religion, the Encouragement of Learning, or the Good of Mankind.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153440:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>To make their Charter go down the better, they have lately publiſhed at <hi>Oxford</hi> [a Book, Entituled, <hi>A Defence of the Rights and Priviledges of the Univerſity of</hi> Oxford] with the Imprimatur of <hi>Jonathan Edwards,</hi> Vice-Can. Oxon. We are concerned that we muſt complain, that we did not meet with that Sincerity in that Book which became that Worthy Body whoſe Name it bore; wherein the Author pretends to Charters which he never ſaw, nor the Univerſity ever had; he hath abuſed Records, and conſulted more what would ſerve his turn, than what was true.</p>
            <p>We would not here be thought to charge that whole Body with ſo much diſingenuity; the do admire and honour them for their Learning, and Integrity, and do paſſionately deſire to maintain a good Correſpondence with them. But we muſt be excuſed, if we ſay, That the Licenſer hath publiſhed thoſe things in the Name of the Univerſity, which the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity will not, nay, cannot with Honour own.</p>
            <p>The great Deſign of that Book is to evince, That nothing is granted in that Charter, which was not their unqueſtionable Right before; how well they have performed it, is the deſign of the following 'Papers to ſhew, wherein we Challenge our Adverſaries to produce one Inſtance in which we have prevaricated, or one Record or Charter which we have mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken or miſrepreſented.</p>
            <p>But admitting their Poſition true, that nothing is granted by this Charter which was not their unqueſtionable Right before, why are they then ſo zealous for a Confirmation of it? All their other Charters are confirmed by the Act of <hi>13 Eliz.</hi> And if all the Grants of this Charter are comprized in their former Charters, then are all the Grants of this Charter confirmed already. If they think the Act <hi>13 Eliz.</hi> not of force enough, or are deſirous to renew it, a Confirmation of all their Charters (except this <hi>11 Car. 1.</hi>) which we ſubmit to, will implicitly confirm the particulars granted by this, if they were included in their former Charters.</p>
            <p>In the following Papers we do not condeſcend to that part of the Book, which ſhews the Wit of the Author, more than his Judgment, or Diſcretion; particularly when he tells us they are our Benefactors, and that we ſpend their Money; but we ſhall take the Liberty only to advertiſe the Author and the Licenſer with this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Obſervation, That it is as hard for Mankind to remember their beginning, as their latter end.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity tell us in their Defence, that they deſire this Confirmation of their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters only to ſecure themſelves from a return of thoſe Encroachments in any ſucceeding Reign, which they experienced in the laſt: If they are ſincere, and deſign no more, then let them Examine this Charter, and if they can find any thing which may ſtrengthen them againſt the Crown, or give them any new Priviledges not relating to us, we ſhall ſubmit to them, and be glad to ſee them Enacted in her <hi>Verba;</hi> but they are miſtaken, the good Arch-biſhop took care only to make them Lords at home, but left them as much in the hands of the King as they were before.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not endeavour to weaken the Reputation of their former Grants, by ſhewing that they were obtained in the dark Times of Popery and Superſtition; and by the mighty Intereſt of thoſe, who had the Seals, as well as Conſciences of Princes in their power; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome of them did not paſs without Reflection in the Ages in which they were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as appears by the Statute <hi>9 H. 4. Cap. 1.</hi> whereby in a General Confirmation of the Charters of all the Cities and Burroughs of <hi>England,</hi> certain Franchiſes granted to the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> are excepted. And the Charter <hi>14 H. 8.</hi> procured by Cardinal <hi>Woolſey,</hi> was ſhortly after the making it branded as unreaſonable, and a Bill paſſed the Houſe of Commons in two ſeveral Parliaments, for the Repeal of it, but theſe Parliaments were diſcontinued before the Bill was perfected.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity themſelves were ſo ſenſible that that Charter was an Invaſion upon us, that in an Anſwer in Chancery <hi>22 H. 8.</hi> to a Bill preferred by the City, they declared they had not, nor ever intended to put it in execution.</p>
            <p>But theſe Charters have been long ſince confirmed, and we ſubmit to them; it being our deſire only to preſerve what is left, and to tranſmit that Liberty, and thoſe Priviledges to our Poſterity, which we have received from our Anceſtors; altho' we cannot but obſerve upon the Statute of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> as an extraordinary thing, that Threeſcore Charters obtained in the dark, and upon Princes who never conſidered, nor perhaps knew the Contents of them, ſhould be confirmed in groſs. But we ſubmit our City, and our ſelves to the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Juſtice of this Parliament, who we are aſſured will be tender of us; and weigh, and well conſider this Charter, which will be the beſt Confutation of it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="case">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153440:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The CASE, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. BY a Charter, bearing date the 30th. day of <hi>March,</hi> 11 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. the Licenſing of Taverns is granted to the Univerſity; and all Magiſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and others, within or without the Univerſity, (except the Chancell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and his Vice-Chancellor) are prohibited to intermeddle with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cenſing of Vintners in <hi>Oxford;</hi> and none are to Licenſe any Ale-houſes there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by the expreſs conſent of the Chancellor, or Vice-Chancellor; Any Act or Statue to the contrary notwithſtanding. And by colour of this Grant they do Licen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Ale-houſe-keepers, and take Recognizances, but did never return any of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Quarter Seſſions until about Ten Years laſt paſt, and have ſince returned th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſame but ſeldom. Whereas by the Statute made 7 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. the Power of granti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Wine-Licenſes in <hi>Oxford,</hi> is veſted in the City: And alſo by the Ancient Chatte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the City, none that is not of the Guild of the City ought to ſell any Wine b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Retail in the ſame. And the Magiſtrates of the City, by ſeveral Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have Power, as their Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace, to Licenſe Inns an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>  Ale-houſes within the City.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity in their Defence pretend that the ſole Licenſing of Taverns wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Originally veſted in them under <hi>Edward</hi> III. But they can ſhew no Grant of any ſuch Power, nor one Licenſe granted in purſuance of it before 7 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. They have indeed by Grant 29 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. the Aſſize and Aſſay of Wine and Ale, but they never ſet up for the Licenſing of Taverns before the 7 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. And if they had no Right before that Statute, we are ſure they can have none ſince; the ſaving in that Statute of the Priviledges of the Univerſity may preſerve an old Right, but connot give them any new: Beſides that Statute doth by expreſs words veſt the Right of Licenſing three Taverns in the City. But admitting the Title to be in the City under 7 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. yet they ſay, that the 12 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. ſaves the Right of the Univerſity, and takes away all pretences of any Right from the City. But we cannot ſee how they will make that out: For if the ſaving in that Statute is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to preſerve the Right of the Univerſity (if they had any) it will be ſurely as ſtrong to ſave the Rights of the City; the Right of the Univerſity, and of all Cities and Towns Corporate being ſaved by the very ſame words.) Their Power over Ale-houſes they claim as a Branch of the Clerkſhip of the Market, which, they ſay, hath been allowed to be ſuch in all Compoſitions with the Town; But they cannot produce one Compoſition for that purpoſe. And if this Power is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the Clerkſhip of the Market, then the Clerks of all the Markets in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have as good a Title to it as themſelves. Before the 5 and 6 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. any Man might ſell Ale without Licenſe, and ſince that Statute no other Conditions are required than are preſcribed in that Act. If the Vice-Chancellor, becauſe he is Clerk of the Market, retains a Negative Voice, and none can ſell Ale without his Licenſe and Conſent, the ſame Power may be as juſtly challenged by the Clerk of any other Market whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By that Charter it is granted, that the Chancellor, Vice-Chancellor, or Proctors, ſhall have Power to ſearch, by Day or by Night, for Suſpicious Perſons, and for ſuch as can give no Account of themſelves; and to puniſh ſuch as are faulty by Impriſonment, Baniſhment, or otherwiſe, at the Will of the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, or Vice-Chancellor, any Statute to the contrary notwithſtanding. And in the ſaid Charter there is a Mandate to the Mayor and Officers of the Town, to be aſſiſtant after the ſearch of ſuch Offenders, and by colour of this Charter, and a pretended Cuſtom, they claim a Power to impoſe Forty ſhillings upon any Perſon (whether Citizen or Stranger) being out of his Houſe or Lodging after Nine of the Clock; which they have exerciſed not only upon private Citizens, but upon the Magiſtrates of the City, in the execution of their Offices, and have impriſoned the Conſtables for keeping Watch and Ward according to the Statute of <hi>Wincheſter:</hi> Which is a great Invaſion upon the Liberty of the Subject, and hath been often ſo declared in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall;</hi> wherefore it is humbly hoped this Parliament will not affirm the ſame by a Law.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity, in their Defence, entitle themſelves to the Night-watch by Cuſtom confirmed by the Charters of <hi>H.</hi> 3. and <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and ratified by Parliament in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time. It is moſt plain, that by the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the 1ſt <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. the Statute of <hi>Winton,</hi> and 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> III. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. the City of <hi>Oxford.</hi> hath
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153440:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Title, and is as much obliged to keep Watch and Ward, as any other City <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Corporation in <hi>England.</hi> Agreeable to theſe Laws were the Charters of thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mes: The Charters of the Univerſity do grant the Night-watch to the City, and oblige the Citizens to keep the Watch, for the Security of themſelves and of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niverſity. The Charter of the 39 <hi>H.</hi> III. which the Univerſity in their Defence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi> in his Charter, cite for the Confirmation of the Univerſity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntereſt in the Night-watch, is full for this purpoſe. The Charter follows <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atim.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="charter">
                        <p>HENRICUS <hi>Dei Gratia,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Omnibus ad quos preſent. literae perventrint ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem: Sciatis quod ad pacem &amp; tranquilitatem Univerſitat. Scholar.</hi> Oxon. <hi>providi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nus, &amp; conceſſimus quod quatuor Aldermanni fiant in</hi> Oxon. <hi>&amp; octo de diſcretioribus &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>egalioribus Burgenſibus</hi> Oxon. <hi>Aſſiſtentes ipſis Aldermannis, qui Omnes Jujent nobis fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>atem, &amp; ſuit Aſſiſtentes, &amp; conſulentes Majori, &amp; Ballivis</hi> Oxon. <hi>ad pacem noſtram Conſervandum, &amp; ad Aſſiſas dicte ville Cuſtodiend. &amp; ad inveſtigand. malefactores, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>erturbatores pacis noſtrae &amp; vagabundos de nocte, &amp; Receptatores Latronum &amp; Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum &amp; corporale preſtent juramentum quod omnia praedicta fideliter obſervabunt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And the other Charter of the Univerſity, 10 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. which they alſo cite, to confirm their Intereſt in the Night-watch, doth but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and confirm this Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>H.</hi> 3. In purſuance of this Charter and theſe Laws, the eight Aſſiſtants of the Mayor, to this day, do ſwear to be aſſiſtant unto the Mayor and Bailiffs, for the finding out ſuch as be Common Diſturbers of the Peace, and of Vagabonds wandring in the Night, and of ſuch as receive Thieves and other Malefactors within the City or Liberties.</p>
            <p>And now let the Univerſity either produce another Title to the Night-Watch, which we are aſſured they cannot, or elſe confeſs, that they had no Title to it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Charter 11 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>Painter</hi>'s Caſe (which in their Defence they produce to juſtifie their Title) is the ſtrongeſt Evidence that they had none. That Caſe was thus:</p>
            <p>In the Year 1609. <hi>Painter</hi> was one of the Bailiffs of <hi>Oxford,</hi> and becauſe he kept Watch and Ward, and purſued Hues and Cries in the Night, was ſued in the Univerſity-Court, by the Vice-Chancellor, and ſentenc'd to pay 20 <hi>l.</hi> for watching ten ſeveral Nights, and for not paying it he was committed to Priſon; and thereupon <hi>Painter</hi> being removed by <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> into the <hi>King's Bench, Henry Samborn,</hi> then High-Sheriff of <hi>Oxford-ſhire,</hi> returned, That the Univerſity had as well the Cuſtody of the City as of the Univerſity, and the preſervation of the Peace, and keeping of Watches, and the Government of them in the City and Univerſity; and that the Univerſity had power to make Laws for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well by Night as by Day, of Scholars and Townſmen: And then ſhews a Statute of the Univerſity, impoſing a Penalty of Forty ſhillings upon Night-Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and ſo juſtified theſe Proceedings againſt <hi>Painter.</hi> Now, the Court of <hi>King's-Bench</hi> having nothing before them but the Return, and their Judgments being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to it, what could they do leſs than remand the Party? But let the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity ſhew how they came by the Cuſtody and Government of the City, and who gave them Power to make By-Laws for the Government of it.</p>
            <p>The City being baffled by the Return in the <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> immediately applied themſelves to the King, and amongſt other things, complained, That the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity had lately claimed, upon Record, the Cuſtody and Government of the City, and Power to make Statutes to bind the Citizens: And thereupon the King refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Matter in their Petition to ſeveral Lords of the Privy Council, who by Award, dated the 22d <hi>June</hi> 1612. reciting that part of the Petition, did declare in theſe words following, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Univerſity and City were two diſtinct Bodies, and had ſeveral and diſtinct Juriſdictions; and that the Univerſity hath not the Charge or Cuſtody of the City<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And in another part of the Award theſe Lords did declare, That the Authority of the Mayor was in its kind abſolute. and in no ſort ſubordinate to the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
            <p>Now let the Univerſity take this whole Caſe together, and they will find they had no reaſon to magnifie themſelves in the Caſe of <hi>Painter,</hi> but to be as much aſhamed of it as they ought to be of ſome others ſince. But we can put them in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153440:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>mind of a late Caſe, and that is, the Caſe of <hi>Dodwell,</hi> in <hi>Eaſter</hi>-Term, 30 <hi>Car.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Common-Pleas,</hi> who being ſued in the Vice-Chancellor's Court for For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Shillings, for being out of his Houſe after Nine of the Clock, moved for a Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and upon long debate, and hearing Council on both ſides, had a Rule for a Prohibition, by the Opinion of the whole Court.</p>
            <p>We do not diſpute the Univerſities Power to walk in the Night, it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for the government of the Univerſity, for ſecuring their own Members, and keeping them within their Colledges; but this is a Walk, and not a Watch and ought not to reſtrain the Officers of the City from doing their Duty, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Watch and Ward, according to the Laws of <hi>England.</hi> Their Predeceſſors were not ſo fond of Power, they were contented to be ſecured by the Watch, without having the Burthen of it: And indeed, it is moſt reaſonable the City ſhould be truſted with this Power, for they are anſwerable for all Miſcarriages committed within the City in the Night-time: If a Man is killed in the Night, and the Man-ſlayer eſcape, the whole Town is to be amerced; and if a man is robbed, and the Felon eſcape, the Hundred is to anſwer. Now, beſides the city it ſelf, we have an Hundred within the Liberty of the City.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Clerkſhip of the Market is granted to the Univerſity, with free Power to diſpoſe of the Stalls and Standing-places in the Market, to have the full Government of the Markets, and to take Toll in the Markets: The Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity hath only a Title to the Clerkſhip of the Market, (and that did anciently belong to the City) but the Markets, and the placing of them, and all Stallage, Piccage, and all other kinds of Toll and Profits therein (except the Toll of Grain) by ancient Uſage and Preſcription, do yet belong unto the City, and for the Profits thereof, the City doth pay a large Fee-Farm to Their Majeſties: So that in caſe that Charter ſhall be confirmed by Parliament, the City will loſe the Markets, and the Profits ariſing thereby, which is a very conſiderable part of that Revenue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Corporation is maintain'd and ſupported.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity in their Defence pretend, that by the Charters <hi>H.</hi> 3. and <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. they have the full Government of the Market, and all incidents to it: Thoſe Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (which are the only Charters they have before 11 <hi>Car.</hi> relating to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets) do grant them only the Aſſize and Aſſay of Bread, Wine, and Ale, and the overſight of Weights and Meaſures. They ſay the City, upon Complaint in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, deſiſted from taking Toll, and in the year 1429. did in Convocation diſown Toll and Stallage, and that a publick Inſtrument was thereupon made; but they do not ſhew by whoſe order that Inſtrument was made, or that it was ever ſealed (nor indeed was it ever ſealed). It ſeems incredible, that the City ſhould renounce their Title to Toll and Stallage, and yet be ſuffered to receive them both throughout all Ages, to this very day. Surely this matter did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to Judge <hi>Jones,</hi> 9 <hi>Car.</hi> who at the requeſt of Arch-biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> Chancellor of the Univerſity, and the Earl of <hi>Berks,</hi> Steward of the City, did undertake the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of this matter, and upon hearing Council on both ſides, did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, That the Market, and things incident to it, and all Toll (except of Grain) did belong to the City. The Univerſity will not allow, that the City do pay a Fee-Farm for the Profits of the Market; but <hi>Dooms-day Book,</hi> and many ancient Inquiſitions in <hi>Eire,</hi> do plainly prove it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Power is given to the Univerſity by that Charter to hold a Court Leet, or view of Frank-pledge, as well over the Town and all the <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> as over the Univerſity, that it ſhall be a full and compleat Leet, and that the Univerſity ſhall have the Perquiſites thereof, and Power to diſtrein for the ſame: Whereas the City hath five Leets, one abſolute and compleat for <hi>Northgate</hi> Hundred, and the four other for the four Wards within the City, and therein have all the Power of Leets, except
<list>
                  <item>1. The Enquiry into the Aſſize and Aſſay of Bread, Beer, and Wine.</item>
                  <item>2. The examination of Weights and Meaſures.</item>
                  <item>3. The puniſhment of Foreſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Regrators.</item>
                  <item>4. The puniſhment of putrid Victuals.</item>
                  <item>5. The puniſhment of thoſe who wear Arms in the Univerſity. And,</item>
                  <item>6. The ſurvey of the High-ways and Streets, which being anciently likewiſe in the City, were 29 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. ſurrender'd into the King's Hands, and by him granted to the Univerſity: And for theſe ſix Points the Univerſity hath ever ſince 29 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. held a qualified Leet over the City and Suburbs, for ſo much, and for ſo many things and Enquiries as were given to the Univerſity 29 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</item>
               </list>
And this Leet is to be ſerved by a mixt Jury, one half
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153440:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>viledg'd men, and the other half free. And the Penalties impoſed by the ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niverſity in this Leet are to be eſtreated, and ſent to the City, and to be levied <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y them to their own uſe, towards their Fee-Farm.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity, in their Defence, preſcribe to an abſolute and compleat Leet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atified by 14 <hi>H.</hi> 8. and confirmed 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> but they cannot ſhew one Court-Roll where they have held a Leet for more Points than we allow them. The Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er 14 <hi>H.</hi> 8. doth not enlarge their old Leet, nor grant them any new one; it gives them Power to return Proceſs to their Leet, but leaves their Juriſdiction as it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound it. Their own Charter 37 <hi>H.</hi> 6. plainly proves, that at that time they had no abſolute and compleat Leet, for that Charter recites, that at that time they could puniſh Nuſances in the High-ways, only by Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, and therefore gives them Power to hold a Leet for that purpoſe; and if they had not conuſance of Nuſances in the High-ways, (which is the moſt ordinary Article of Enquiry) moſt certainly they have no compleat Leet by Preſcription. They ſay we cannot prove, that the Profits of their Leet belong to us; but if they conſult the ſame Charter of 37 <hi>H.</hi> 6. they will need no other Proof of it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By the ſaid Charter it is granted, that the Univerſity ſhall have Power to make Corporations, Orders, and Laws, to bind all the Inhabitants in the City, and may puniſh the Breaches of them according to the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> or the Statutes and Cuſtoms of the Univerſity, by diſcommoning or otherwiſe. Whereas the City and Univerſity are two diſtinct Corporations, and the one in no ſort ſubordinate to the other; and therefore it is not reaſonable that the Citizens ſhould be bound by Laws which they never conſented to, by themſelves or their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives.</p>
            <p>To maintain their Power to bind us by their By-Laws, they ſay, 1st, We are a Corporation alwaies ſubordinate to them: 2d, That we take an Oath of Fealty to them every Year; and 3d, Are accountable to them in their Court. The firſt of theſe is confuted by the Lords of the Council, which we have taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of before, and the other two are groſs Miſtakes: We do not, nor ever did take an Oath of Fealty to them; nor are we otherwiſe accountable to them, than all the People of <hi>England</hi> are, in being liable to anſwer there to any perſonal Action, where the Plaintiff is a Scholar.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By that Charter a Grant is made to the Univerſity of two Coroners; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as time out of Mind, the City hath had two Coroners, who have ſate upon all perſons, as well priviledg'd as free, until the making that Charter: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the City having an Intereſt in the Coroners, before that Grant, the Grant to the Univerſity is void, and Inquiſitions taken under it <hi>eoram non Judice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Univerſity make no Title to this before the Charter 11 <hi>Car.</hi> but only ſay, That the Chancellor having before that time Power to try all Felonies, the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's Power was lodged in them: But they will find, if they look back, that we alwaies aſſigned a Coroner for their Members before that Charter.</p>
            <p n="7">7. By that Charter Townſmen are to be anſwerable for their Families in buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling all Wares where either Party is a Scholar; and alſo for all ſuch perſons as they ſhall harbour in their Houſes above three Nights; and no Townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is to build any Cottages, without the expreſs leave of the Chancellor or Vice-Chancellor: Which are Reſtraints inconſiſtent with the <hi>Liberty</hi> of an <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Univerſity juſtifie theſe Hardſhips by their reſemblance to the <hi>Laws</hi> before the Conqueſt; but theſe Gentlemen ſhould conſider, that thoſe Laws were then made to ſecure the Prince, and not to enable Subjects to tyrannize over one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; they were then apparent Badges of Slavery, but neceſſary to ſupport the Prince in his new Conqueſts. But what occaſion have the Univerſity for any ſuch Power, unleſs they would have Soveraign Power in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and make the <hi>Citizens</hi> Subjects and Slaves to their Authority?</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Univerſity doth pretend to have a Power to diſcommon Citizens at their Pleaſure, and to inhibit all Priviledg'd Perſons to have any Commerce or Trading with them; which they ſometimes uſe, to the Ruine of the Citizens and their Families.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity preſcribe to this as an <hi>ancient Right,</hi> but they do not pretend to any Grant of it before that <hi>Charter.</hi> And for their Uſage, if that alone would give a Right, they would then be able to juſtifie many things which they have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153440:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>reaſon to be aſhamed of. But they ſay the City doth the ſame thing, who make it a Condition of their Leaſes, not to let their Houſes to Scholars, nor to grind at any other than their Mills. We deny that we have any ſuch Condition in our Leaſes relating to Scholars; and for the grinding at our Mills, the Covenant doth but purſue the Cuſtom of the City; for all perſons reſiding within the City do owe Suit to grind at our Mills, and we have at all times, in our Courts, amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced divers perſons for not grinding there.</p>
            <p n="9">9. By the ſaid Charter it is granted, that Scholars, their Servants, and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Univerſity, ſhall not be forced to appear at Muſters, or contribute thereunto; and that they ſhall be diſcharged of Subſidies, Reliefs, Impoſitions, Contributions, and Sums of Money then granted, or hereafter to be granted, any Act of Parliament, Statute, or Ordinance to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Univerſity entitle themſelves to theſe Immunities by Cuſtom, and ſay, All foreign Univerſities enjoy the ſame Priviledge. We know of no ſuch Cuſtom, nor are we concerned to enquire what is uſed in foreign Univerſities, but we may with ſome aſſurance affirm, that no Univerſity in the World doth pretend to exempt ſo vaſt a Body from publick Duties as they do. Originally the Univerſity had no Priviledge at all; 28 <hi>H.</hi> 3. they had a Grant of Priviledge in their Courts for Clerks only, but they ſoon enlarged their Juriſdiction, and in the 18th Year of <hi>E.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. gave the City reaſon to complain in Parliament, that the Univerſity did challenge others to be priviledg'd, who were not Scholars; and thereupon it was order'd by the King in Parliament, by the conſent of both Bodies, that theſe and no others ſhould have the Priviledge of the Univerſity, <hi>viz.</hi> Clerks and their Servants, Parchment-makers, Limners, (that is, the Guilders and Painters of Books) Writers, Barbers, and the Livery-men of Clerks: But the Univerſity ſoon broke through this Compoſition; and therefore 37 <hi>H.</hi> 6. we were forced to come to a new Agreement, and then it was agreed, that theſe only ſhould have the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Univerſity, <hi>viz.</hi> Scholars and Clerks dwelling within the Univerſity, and their daily continual Servants, the Steward, Feodmen and Bailiffs, Stationers, Book-binders, Limners, Writers, Parchment-makers, Barbers, Cators, Manciples, Spencers, Cooks, Lavenders, and the Servants of Scholars, taking Wages without Fraud. Thus we ſee from how narrow a beginning this Priviledge hath ſprung up, almoſt to eclipſe the whole Town. But they tell us, That Priviledg'd Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who uſe Merchandiſe in the City, ſhall be taxed for their Merchandiſe; we are beholden to them for that: But this Charter makes no ſuch diſtinction, that is a general Exemption to all priviledg'd Perſons, from all Taxes and Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whatſoever: And it is fit to be conſidered, whether, if this Bill paſs, all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom they ſhall priviledge, will not be diſcharged from all Duties upon the Acts for the ſettling the Militia, and other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Duties now in force, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity have already pretended, upon the ſtrength of this Charter only, That priviledg'd perſons are exempted from thoſe Acts, and they will have good Reaſon for it, when that Charter ſhall have the Sanction of an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The Univerſity, by means of a Compoſition made ſhortly after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict 29 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. and confirmed by the ſaid Charter, do require the Mayor and 62 Citizens with him yearly, upon <hi>Scholaſticas-day,</hi> (which is the Tenth day of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi>) to repair to St. <hi>Marys</hi> Church in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and to make an Oblation there, upon the high Altar, of 63 pence, for the Souls of 63 Scholars ſlain in the time of King <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. This being in the Original groſs Superſtition, is too great a Badge of Popery to be required in a Proteſtant Univerſity.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity confeſs the Superſtition, but ſay, The Maſs and Offering were enjoyned at the Requeſt of the City, in exchange for the yearly Sum of One hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Marks, which were firſt impoſed upon them: But the contrary is moſt true, for the Award was made by the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> who had no Power to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the yearly Payment of 100 Marks, and the 100 Marks were only a Penalty to ſecure the performance of the Superſtition, and that appears by the Covenant of the City, 14. <hi>May,</hi> 31 <hi>E.</hi> 3. to ſay Maſs, and make the Offering, and the Bond of the City 15. <hi>May,</hi> 31 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. to pay 100 Marks yearly, and a Writing of the Univerſity, 16. <hi>May,</hi> 31 <hi>E.</hi> 3. whereby the Univerſity agree, that the 100 Marks yearly ſhall not be paid, if the Superſtition is duly obſerved, ſo that the Award
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153440:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>intended the performance of the Superſtition, and not the Payment of the 100 Marks yearly. But the Univerſity ſay, that this Superſtition, by conſent of both Parties, in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, was changed into a Sermon, a Communion, and an Offering: We find no Footſteps of any ſuch exchange, but if any ſuch there were, the Univerſity have been ever ſince very fond of their old Superſtition, for they never ſince preached, or had a Communion upon that day, but they do yet require us to Offer as heretofore: And in the year 1660, they petitioned the King and Council, and therein ſet forth, That the Mayor and 62 Citizens ought to make an Oblation of 63 pence, in Memory of a great Slaughter of Scholars, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted upon <hi>Scholaſticas-day,</hi> and prayed an Order for the continuance of it, and it was ordered accordingly.</p>
            <p n="11">11. By the ſaid Charter it is granted, That Scholars, or Priviledg'd perſons, ſhall not be impleaded in the Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> for ſuch things as the Chancellor hath cognizance of; and that they ſhall be diſmiſſed from thence without plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Priviledge, or paying their Fees, which doth often fall out to be a very great Oppreſſion to the Officers and Miniſters of Juſtice; for if upon demand of the Vice-Chancellor they do not diſcharge ſuch priviledg'd perſons, the Vice Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, by colour of this Clauſe, doth impriſon the Bailiff, as on the 20. of <hi>October,</hi> in the Year 1689, he did one <hi>Edward Adams,</hi> a ſworn Bailiff, for not diſcharging <hi>Henry Wildgooſe,</hi> who was arreſted at the Suit of the City, by a Writ iſſuing out of the Court of Common-Pleas. And by colour of the ſaid Clauſe, if any perſon ſue a priviledg'd man in any of the Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the ſaid Vice-Chancellor doth cite the Plaintiff into the Court of the Univerſity, for breach of their Statutes, and doth condemn him in Expences, for ſueing a priviledg'd perſon out of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</p>
            <p>To this part of our Caſe they Harangue upon the Antiquity and Uſefulneſs of their Court. We do not complain of their Courts, but the abuſe of them; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may ſeem ſtrange that any Government ſhould ſuffer a Court ſo repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Laws of the Country.</p>
            <p>They ſeem to inſinuate that the Impriſonment of the Bayliff hath been twice at leaſt acknowledged in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi> But we believe the Vice-Chancellor would ſcarce be able to maintain it, if the Bayliff ſhould bring an Action of Falſe Impriſonment againſt him. We never heard of any ſuch Caſe, and if there were, we have reaſon to believe, it was dreſs'd up as <hi>Painter</hi>'s was.</p>
            <p n="12">12. By the ſaid Charter it is granted, that Priviledged Men ſhall have as much Liberty to Trade, as the Freemen of the ſaid City; and by colour of this Grant the ſaid Univerſity do take upon them to ſet up Trades, and to Licenſe certain Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whom they call Priviledged Perſons, openly to uſe Trades, and to ſell Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes within the ſaid City and Suburbs by Retail; which is contrary to the Ancient Charters, Cuſtoms, and Priviledges of the ſaid City, and to certain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and Agreements made between the ſaid Univerſity and City.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity entitle Priviledged Men to Trade by Preſcription, ſaved by the oldeſt Charters of the City, allowed in Parliament 18 <hi>Ed. 1ſt.</hi> declared by the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>H.</hi> 8. and ratified by the 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> It is moſt plain they can have no Right by Preſcription ſo large as this Charter, for the Charter is general, and gives them Power to ſet up any Trades, and the uſage hath always been againſt them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides their own Charter 12 <hi>Ap.</hi> 10. <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. is an Evidence that they had no Title by Preſcription to uſe Trades in <hi>Oxford,</hi> for that Charter recites, that the Burgeſſes of the Town would not ſuffer any that were not of their Guild, to ſell Linnen or Woollen Cloath in <hi>Oxford</hi> by Retail; and therefore grants that others may ſell ſuch Wares by Retail, or Whole-ſale. But the City having a Right by Preſcription to exclude Foreigners, that Grant will not take it from them: And we can ſhew the Univerſity many of their Petitions to the King, complaining that the City did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all Perſons that were not of their Guild from ſelling Wares within their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, which had been needleſs if they had Power to ſet up Trades, and ſell Wares in <hi>Oxford,</hi> as well as the Citizens.</p>
            <p>Nor is it more true that the oldeſt Charter of the City ſaves their Right of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in <hi>Oxford;</hi> the oldeſt Charters the City hath, are granted by <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, King <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Third: The firſt of theſe grants and confirms to the City all Cuſtoms which they had in the time of his Grandfather, <hi>(viz.) Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. Guildam ſuam Mercatoriam,</hi> with all its Liberties; and that none that is not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:153440:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of that Guild ſhall Merchandize in the City or Suburbs; together with all Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Cuſtoms which <hi>London</hi> had. So that by this very Charter it appears, that it was the Cuſtom of the City to exclude Foreigners in the time of the Grand father of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, who was <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt; and none of theſe Charters make mention of the Univerſity, or ſave their Rights. It is true, in a Charter of the City in time of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, being an Exemplification of theſe Charters of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, King <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, and a Grant of many other Particulars, there is a ſaving of the Univerſity Rights in general. But that Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth not grant to us any Right of ſole Trading, (as indeed none can) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaving cannot be applyed to it.</p>
            <p>For the 18 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. if they conſider that, they will find no Reaſon to preſume that an Allowance to them to uſe Trades, there are no words in it relating to Trades. It only ſettles (as we have ſaid before) what Perſons ſhall have the Priviledge of the Univerſity, which we deny to relate to Trade, and if it did, if they will ſtand to that Compoſition, they will find their Priviledge much more narrow than they now enjoy it; and if they will wave their Encroachments upon us, and go back to the Compoſition 18 <hi>Edw.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. or to the other of 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>H.</hi> 6. which their Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors took to be great Improvements of their Priviledges, we will readily allow all Perſons within thoſe Compoſitions, as much Priviledge as they will deſire for them.</p>
            <p>For the Charter 14 <hi>H.</hi> 8. that was a great Encroachment upon our Trade, but yet nothing ſo large as this. We have been the larger upon this Branch relating to Trade, becauſe we know what would become of our Corporation, if we once allow whom they think fit to matriculate a Right to Trade amongſt us. A Power to Trade without the incumbrance of chargeable Offices, by which the City doth ſubſiſt, would ſoon draw all the Inhabitants of the Town into their Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Whereas by certain Compoſitions heretofore made between the ſaid Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity and City, the Menial Servants of all Scholars, and all their other Servants taking Wages without Fraud or Deceit, are to enjoy the Priviledges of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; the ſaid Univerſity, upon pretence of later Grants, have fraudulently, and with an intent to weaken the Government of the ſaid City, granted colourable Priviledges to divers Members of the ſaid City, and upon pretence that they were become the Under-Groom, Gardiner, or Officer of ſome Colledge, have matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated them, and whilſt they have continued Members of the City have admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred unto them an Oath to the Effect following, <hi>(viz.) You ſhall ſwear, That you ſhall not attempt any Cauſe of yours before the Mayor, or Bayliffs of</hi> Oxford, <hi>neither ſhall you anſwer before any of them as your Judge, ſo long as you ſhall continue a Priviledged Perſon. So God, &amp;c.</hi> Which is in terms repugnant to the Oath which every Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the City doth take at the time of his Admiſſion into the Liberties of the ſaid City; and particularly they have within the ſpace of Three Years laſt paſt matriculated one <hi>William Turton,</hi> upon pretence that the ſaid <hi>William Turton</hi> was Gardiner of <hi>Exeter</hi> Colledge; whereas the ſaid <hi>William Turton</hi> was a Freeman of the ſaid City, and did continue to uſe the Trade of a Vintner during his Life, and obtained the Title of the ſaid Office only to avoid the bearing ſuch Offices in the ſaid City, as his condition and ſubſtance had made him capable of. They have alſo upon the ſame terms matriculated one <hi>Henry Wildgooſe</hi> a Freeman, and one of the Common-Council of the ſaid City, who being apprehenſive that he ſhould be choſen into the Office of Chamberlain of the ſaid City, did, to avoid the ſame, about two days before the Election for the ſaid Office, procure himſelf to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triculated upon pretence that he was a Groom to one Doctor <hi>Iriſh,</hi> although the ſaid <hi>Henry Wildgooſe</hi> did, and yet doth continue the Trade of a Painter within the ſaid City, and hath no further Relation to the ſaid Doctor <hi>Iriſh,</hi> than to Protect himſelf againſt the ſaid City, and by colour of the ſaid Matriculation, the ſaid <hi>Henry Wildgooſe</hi> being Elected Chamberlain of the ſaid City, did, and yet doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to accept the ſaid Office, and is protected in his Diſobedience by the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; by which means other Citizens are encouraged to withdraw themſelves from their Majeſties Service in the ſaid City.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity do not in their Defence deny they have matriculated <hi>Wildgooſe</hi> and <hi>Turton,</hi> but ſay, they matriculated <hi>Wildgooſe</hi> as Servant to Doctor <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and as a Limner, and <hi>Turton</hi> as a Vintner. As for <hi>Wildgooſe,</hi> an Action being brought
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:153440:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>againſt him in the Court of R. B. at <hi>Weſt. Term. Mich.</hi> 1. <hi>W. &amp; M.</hi> for refuſing the Office of Chamberlain, the Univerſity demanded Cognizance of the Cauſe, becauſe he was Servant to Doctor <hi>Iriſh,</hi> but it appearing to the Court, that <hi>Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gooſe</hi> was a Freeman, and a Member of the Common-Council, and an Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, and kept Shop in the City, and that he was matriculated but two days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Election, and had declared that he would be matriculated to avoid the Election, the Court were of Opinion that the City were abuſed in it, and that the Matriculation was fraudulent, and therefore denyed them Cognizance. The Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity not contented with this Reſolution, in <hi>Hillary</hi> Term following moved the Court again, and having found in the Compoſitions 18 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. and 37 <hi>H.</hi> 6. that Limners were to have the Priviledge of the Univerſity, they demanded Cognizance becauſe he was a Limner (tho' they thought of no ſuch thing when they matricu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated him) but it appearing to the Court that Limners were ſuch only as did adorn Books by painting them with Gold and Water-colours before Printing was known, and that <hi>Wildgooſe</hi> was a Painter-ſtainer; and it appearing alſo to the Court by the very Compoſitions which they produced, that none was to have the Priviledge of the Univerſity that got it by Fraud or Malengine, they did again deny to grant them Cognizance. For the Caſe of <hi>Turton,</hi> they find they cannot juſtifie his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triculation as Servant to a Colledge, though that was his firſt Title, they will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now entitle him as the Univerſity Vintner: Whether he ſtood upon that, or the firſt Title, it is plain he was matriculated only to elude the Election of the City, and to defeat their Power over him; they never pretended to Priviledge any Vintner before as ſuch, nor have they any Foundation for it by uſage or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. The Reaſon of allowing Priviledge is, that Scholars ſhall not be taken from their Studies to Anſwer in the King's Courts; but that Reaſon will not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie this Caſe, nor is a Vintner ſo neceſſary an Attendant upon the Univerſity, that he may not do his Duty to the Government. They have never before pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by their Priviledge to diſcharge the Members of any Corporation from their Duty they owe to it; they may with as much Reaſon practice the ſame thing upon the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> as upon us, we are as much a diſtinct Corporation from the Univerſity as they are.</p>
            <p>The Univerſity ſeem to take it ill, that the City was not left to prove their Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes againſt the Matriculation of <hi>Wildgooſe</hi> in their Court, and there to receive Juſtice from their hands. But they muſt excuſe us, if we thought them too far Parties to be Indifferent Judges.</p>
            <p>And now having followed them through all the parts of their Defence, we do Appeal even to the Univerſity, whether it doth not behove us to oppoſe the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this Charter, and whether any of the Particulars which we have charged upon it as new Grants, were their unqueſtionable Rights before. But the Author of the Defence tells us, That <hi>the</hi> Proviſo <hi>in the Bill fully ſecures the Rights, Liberties, and Immunities of the City, and puts them wholly out of the reach of the Bill.</hi> That <hi>as the Confirmation is by Act of Parliament, ſo is the</hi> Proviſo <hi>made by the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and therefore no greater Power can ſecure their Rights, than that, which as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually reſtrains their Encroachments.</hi> And in another place, That <hi>the force of the Clauſe is ſo evident to all Men of Senſe and Law, that in reference to the City it wholly diſables and deſtroys the Bill.</hi> But let us conſider this Charter and the Bill together, and we ſhall be able to Judge of theſe Aſſertions, and whether the Author hath offered either Law or Senſe to maintain them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Charter grants to the Univerſity divers expreſs Powers over the City, and many things which the City by good Title are in poſſeſſion of: And the Bill enacts, That this Charter ſhall be good, effectual, and available in the Law, to all Intents and Purpoſes, as amply, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as if the ſame were recited <hi>verbatim</hi> in the ſaid Act, with a <hi>Proviſo,</hi> that that Act ſhall not be to the Prejudice of the Priviledges and Liberties of Right belonging to the City, but that they ſhall be as free as they were before. Now this Act referring to that Charter, all Matters comprized in it will as fully be enacted, as if they were expreſly enacted in the body of the Act, without relation to the Charter; and then the Caſe will be no more, than if the Act ſhould expreſly grant to the Univerſity ſuch Eſtates and ſuch Powers, provided <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſhall have no ſuch Eſtates nor Powers; which is to grant and not to grant, which every man will allow to be repugnant and void: So that a Confirmation may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153440:6"/>be by Act of Parliament, and yet a <hi>Proviſo</hi> in that Act may be void; their Rights may be ſecured, and their Encroachments not reſtrained.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The City of <hi>Oxford</hi> are entituled unto the ſeveral Priviledges before ſpecified (except the Power of granting Wine and Ale Licences) by Uſage and Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only, and therefore they can never have any benefit of this <hi>Proviſo,</hi> without proving the particular Uſage and Cuſtom at the time of making this Act, which in a ſhort time will be very difficult for them to do: But were this matter leſs clear, yet we humbly hope, that it will not be expected that we ſhould hazard our ancient Liberties, and the Freedom of our ſelves and our Poſterity, upon a Moot Point.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Admitting this <hi>Proviſo</hi> would effectually ſecure our ancient Rights, yet will it not prevent the operation of the Statute upon many things, which although the City make no Title to, yet would they greatly ſuffer, if they ſhould be veſted in the Univerſity. As for inſtance; in <hi>Oxford</hi> the Market is free for all manner of Grain; this Charter grants the Toll of Grain to the Univerſity, (which is void as a Grant) if this Parliament confirm it, they will have a Right to that Toll; which will be very injurious to the City, and all the neighbouring Country. We could give many Inſtances of this nature.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, If the Univerſity believe themſelves, and are in earneſt when they tell us, that the force of this <hi>Proviſo,</hi> in reference to the City, wholly diſables and deſtroys the Bill, they cannot reaſonably deſire a Confirmation of this Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter charged with the <hi>Proviſo,</hi> for the <hi>Proviſo,</hi> according to them, will have the effect of an Exception of this Charter; for if they confirm this Charter ſubject to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo,</hi> then will the <hi>Proviſo,</hi> as to all the new Eſtates and Powers in the Charter rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the City, wholly diſable and deſtroy the Bill, which comprehend the whole Charter (except the Power of Printing). Which, and whatſoever elſe may be to their Advantage, and not injurious to us, we deſire may be ſpecially enacted. And if the Univerſity are ſincere, we ſee no reaſon why they ſhould be ſo fond of this Charter, unleſs they would lay the Foundation of Eternal Suits and Controverſies.</p>
            <p>We ſhall not concern our ſelves to ſhew, that this <hi>Proviſo</hi> takes no care of all the Inhabitants of the City, who are Members of neither Body, and yet are very nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, nor of all the Gentlemen of the Kingdom who come to <hi>Oxford,</hi> but leaves them ſubject to all the extraordinary Powers of that Charter.</p>
            <p>But we ſhall not engage others in our Difficulties, nor be Suitors for more than our ſelves, for we cannot fear that we ſhall be abandoned in this Reign, who have been protected by the Government in all Ages; Kings have been our Nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the whole Legiſlature our Protection; we have Monuments of Royal Bounty in every Reign ſince <hi>Henry</hi> II. and are able to produce the Broad Seal of every King ſince: And ſhall one Bill deſtroy the Bounty of ſo many Kings? Shall we be obliged to date our Misfortunes from a <hi>Proteſtant Reign?</hi> God forbid. Their Majeſties, and this Parliament, who have done ſo glorious things for the whole Nation, and have almoſt ſacrificed themſelves to do us good, will aſſuredly protect us, and ſuffer us to partake in that common Liberty, which they have entailed upon all the People of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
